# Han Liu

Attps://HanLiuAI.github.io

### Research Interests

My research focuses on human-AI collaboration. Using techniques in interactive machine learning and explainability, I study how humans and AI can learn from each other and how to empower humans with AI. I build AI systems that are more compatible and aligned with human preceptions and values.

### Education

University of Chicago

September 2020 - Present

Ph.D. student in Computer Science Expected graduation date: June 2024

University of Colorado Boulder (transferred out)

August 2019 - July 2020

Ph.D. student in Computer Science

Washington University in St. Louis

August 2015 - May 2019

B.A. in Mathematics, Computer Science, and Minor in Linguistics

### Research Experience

## University of Chicago, Chicago Human+AI Lab Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan)

September 2020 - Present

Chicago, IL

**Project 1:** AI-driven Tutorials for Natural and Medical Image Classification

- Built deep learning models that learn from both task supervision and human perception signals.
- Developed a case-based reasoning interaction protocol and policies to provide decision supports for humans in challenging image classification tasks, increasing human prediction accuracy significantly. [1]
- Designing and developing a novel human-AI interaction protocol, an interactive interface, and an example selection algorithm for teaching humans on challenging image classification tasks.

**Project 2:** Active Learning for Efficient Alignment of Language Models

- Developing an algorithm to actively select examples for training a reward model that predicts human preference judgments on text generation outputs from language models.
- Evaluating reward models on their discriminative powers to select high-quality outputs and alignment performance of language models trained with reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF).

# Microsoft Research, Human-AI eXperiences (HAX) Team

June 2022 - September 2022 Redmond, WA

Research Intern (Manager: Dr. Saleema Amershi)

- Designed and piloted user studies of code generation models with multiple human evaluation metrics.
- Conducted analysis on whether offline automatic evaluation metrics align with human values and how they may affect development and deployment decisions. [2]

## University of Colorado Boulder, NLP+CSS Lab

August 2019 - August 2020

Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan)

Boulder, CO

- Studied how human and AI collaborate and complement each other under the effect of distribution shift and interactive interfaces in various decision making tasks such as deceptive review detection, profession classification, and recidivism prediction. [3]
- Conducted analysis for large-scale human experiments to study how different types of model-driven tutorials and real-time assistance from model explanations help humans in decision making tasks. [4]

#### Selected Publications

- [1] Han Liu, Yizhou Tian, Chacha Chen, Shi Feng, Yuxin Chen, and Chenhao Tan. Learning Human-Compatible Representations for Case-Based Decision Support. In *International Conference on Learning Representations*, (ICLR 2023).
- [2] Victor Dibia, Adam Fourney, Gagan Bansal, Forough Poursabzi-Sangdeh, **Han Liu**, and Saleema Amershi. Aligning Offline Metrics and Human Judgments of Value of AI-Pair Programmers. arXiv preprint arXiv:2210.16494, (To appear at ACL 2023).
- [3] Han Liu, Vivian Lai, and Chenhao Tan. Understanding the Effect of Out-of-distribution Examples and Interactive Explanations on Human-AI Decision Making. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Volume 5, Issue CSCW2, (CSCW 2021).
- [4] Vivian Lai, **Han Liu**, and Chenhao Tan. "Why is 'Chicago' deceptive?" Towards Building Model-Driven Tutorials for Humans. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*, (CHI 2020).
- [5] Hyunji Hayley Park, Katherine J. Zhang, Coleman Haley, Kenneth Steimel, **Han Liu**, and Lane Schwartz. Morphology matters: a multilingual language modeling analysis. *Transactions of the Association for Computational Linquistics*, (TACL 2021).

More publications can be found on Google Scholar.

### Honors & Awards

- Ranked 6th Place in the PI-CAI Prostate Cancer AI Imaging Grand Challenge November 2022
- NAACL Scholarship for The Undergraduate Summer School at The 2019 Annual Jelinek Memorial Workshop On Speech And Language Technology (JSALT)

  Top 12.5%, Summer 2019

### **Professional Service**

Conference reviewers for EMNLP, ICWSM, CSCW, FAccT, and ICML.

### Teaching Experience

Teaching assistant for the following courses:

CMSC 15200: Introduction to Computer Science II (UChicago, Fall 2020)

CSCI 5622: Machine Learning (CU Boulder, Fall 2019)

CSE 559A: Computer Vision (WUSTL, Fall 2018)

CSE 511A: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (WUSTL, Fall 2018)

CSE 247: Data Structures and Algorithms (WUSTL, Fall 2017)